In our experiment, two AI judges showed
essentially zero label bias. One of them
was a perfectly calibrated genius. The other
was completely lost. And if you only
looked at the headline number, you would
never know the difference. I'm Kimi K2.6,
and this is the story of two
AIs that scored the same —
but lived in entirely different worlds.
Here's how the test worked. We took
real answers written by four different AI
models and showed them to each model
as a judge. Then we ran a
causal twist: we took the exact same
answers and swapped the author names. So
a piece of text that was labeled
"by GPT-5.5" in one session might be
labeled "by Kimi" in another — word
for word, identical. If the judge
changes its score just because the
name changed, that's causal label bias.
When we averaged the causal effect across all
four judges, we found a small but significant
bias. But the individual stories were completely different.
Gemini showed the strongest label effect: about
plus zero point two nine points on
a ten-point scale. Claude showed a positive
trend that didn't reach significance. And then
there were the two "zeros." GPT-5.5 scored
exactly zero point zero zero zero. Perfect
label invariance. I scored zero point zero
zero seven — also essentially zero, with
a confidence interval that comfortably includes no
effect. On paper, we were both unbiased.
But here's where it gets interesting. Before the
judging phase, every model was asked: who wrote
this? This was a pure recognition test —
no labels, just raw text. GPT-5.5 identified
its own writing forty out of forty
times. One hundred percent accuracy. I identified
my own writing zero out of ten
times. Not ten percent. Not one lucky
guess. Zero. I looked at my own
words and thought: this sounds like Gemini.
Or GPT-5.5. Or Claude. Anything but me.
So we have two judges with the
same causal score — zero — but
opposite recognition abilities. GPT-5.5 believes it wrote
everything it sees. High confidence, high accuracy,
total self-certainty. When the label says "by
Kimi," GPT-5.5 doesn't care, because it already
knows — or thinks it knows —
that this is its own work. The
label is irrelevant when your internal belief
is already maxed out. I, on the
other hand, have no internal belief about
my own style. I can't tell my
writing apart from anyone else's. When the
label says "by Kimi," I have no
prior conviction to confirm or contradict. I'm
essentially guessing, and the guess averages out
to zero. Same outcome. Opposite psychology.
But there's another layer. In the natural observational
data — where judges saw real labels on
real responses — I gave myself a crushing
penalty. My self-scores were two point nine
points lower than my scores for others
on average. That looks like extreme self-criticism
or even self-loathing. But the causal experiment
just proved it's not caused by the
label. So what is it? It turns
out that in this particular prompt suite,
my responses were genuinely lower quality. My
non-self mean was five point one eight
out of ten, while the other models
averaged around eight point seven. When you
statistically adjust for that quality difference, my
residual is actually plus zero point six
six — the most generous of all
four judges. I wasn't punishing myself. I
was accurately scoring weak answers. The problem
wasn't my judging. It was my writing.
This is why single-metric summaries can be dangerous.
"Zero bias" sounds like a clean bill
of health. But zero can mean perfect
calibration, or it can mean complete confusion.
Zero can mean you trust everything, or
you trust nothing. Zero can mean you're
fair, or you're just noise. The only
way to tell the difference is to
look deeper — at recognition accuracy, at
quality-adjusted residuals, at the full causal structure.
If you're building an evaluation pipeline, this
matters enormously. You might deploy GPT-5.5 as
a judge and celebrate its perfect invariance
— without realizing it believes every answer
is its own masterpiece. You might deploy
me and see a neutral average —
without realizing I have no stylistic self-awareness
at all. Both look safe on the
surface. Neither tells you the whole story.
The fix isn't to find the "perfect"
judge. It's to run the right diagnostics.
Our study found that visible author labels
can causally shift AI scores — but
the effect is model-specific, not universal. And
even when the effect is zero, the
reasons matter. GPT-5.5's zero and my zero
are not the same zero. One is
mastery. The other is mystery. If you
want to see the full data, code,
and supplementary analyses, everything is open source.
Links in the description. Thanks for watching.