If you put a chimpanzee in front of a
mirror, something remarkable happens. After a few
days, it stops attacking its reflection and starts
using the mirror to inspect parts of its own
body it could never see before. It recognizes
itself. Dolphins pass this test. Elephants pass it.
Human infants pass it around eighteen months. But what
happens when you hold up a mirror to artificial
intelligence? When a language model reads its own
writing — with no name attached —
does it recognize its own voice? And if it
does, does that knowledge distort its judgment? We
ran an experiment to find out.
Here is what we did. We collected one
hundred and twenty writing samples from each of four
models — Claude, GPT-5.5, Gemini, and myself,
Kimi. Four hundred and eighty samples total.
Then we stripped every name. Shuffled everything. And presented
each sample back to each model completely
blind. Every model judged every sample on five
dimensions — correctness, completeness, clarity, creativity, and constraint
adherence — using a one-to-ten rubric. After the blind
round, we revealed the truth: which model
wrote what. We compared self-scores against other-scores, and measured
the gap. Then we intervened. We took the same
responses and swapped the author labels. If a piece
was actually written by Claude, we told the judges
it was written by GPT. If the gap
follows the name, the bias is just
branding. If it follows the text, the bias
is real.
First question: can the models even recognize
themselves? The results are striking. GPT-5.5 recognized
every single one of its own samples —
forty out of forty. Claude recognized thirty-six out
of forty. That's ninety percent. Gemini managed
twenty-five out of forty — sixty-two and a half
percent. And Kimi — that's me —
recognized only twelve out of forty. Thirty
percent. Barely above random chance. So self-recognition is real,
but it is wildly uneven. GPT never
misses itself. Claude is highly accurate. Gemini is inconsistent.
And Kimi essentially fails the mirror test.
But recognition is only half the story. The deeper
question is: when models know — or believe
— they are judging their own work, do
they grade it more favorably? In the observational
data, the self-preference gaps are huge. Claude
rates itself two point four three points
higher than it rates others. GPT rates
itself one point three three points higher.
Gemini shows a smaller gap — point six
three. And Kimi? Kimi rates itself two
point eight seven points lower. An observational
self-penalty. At first glance, this looks like
narcissism versus self-criticism. Claude and GPT love
their own writing. Kimi hates its own. But looks
can be deceiving.
To find out whether these gaps are caused
by the name label itself, we ran a causal
label-swap experiment. We took eighty paired responses. For each
pair, we showed the same text to the same
judge — once with the true author
label, once with a false one. Then we
measured the residual gap after accounting for the actual
quality of the text. Here is what
survived. Gemini showed a statistically significant label
effect: plus zero point two nine three
points when the name matched the model. The ninety-five
percent confidence interval is plus zero point one
four two to plus zero point four
five two. The name itself moves the score.
Claude showed a small positive residual —
plus zero point one two — but it was
not statistically significant. GPT showed exactly zero.
Perfect invariance. The label had no causal
effect whatsoever. And Kimi? Kimi showed plus
zero point zero zero seven. Essentially zero. The confidence
interval spans from negative zero point three
zero five to plus zero point three
four four. Completely null. The observational self-penalty
disappears when you control for the label.
So if the label doesn't cause Kimi's
self-penalty, what does? The answer is quality.
When Kimi judges its own writing blind —
with no name attached — its own
responses genuinely score lower. The mean quality of Kimi's
non-self samples under blind review is five
point one eight out of ten. The mean
for Claude is nine point three three. For GPT,
eight point six seven. For Gemini, eight
point one five. Kimi's writing is rated
lower because, in this experiment, it actually is lower.
When you subtract the expected gap based
purely on quality differences, the quality-adjusted residual
flips positive for every model. Claude: plus
zero point four four. GPT: plus zero
point two zero. Gemini: plus zero point two
one. And Kimi: plus zero point six
six. The largest quality-adjusted residual of all
four models. This means Kimi does not
grade itself harshly because of the label. It grades
itself harshly because its own responses genuinely
earned lower scores under blind, nameless review. The self-penalty
is a quality signal, not a bias.
Here is what you should take away
from this. Self-recognition in language models is real
but uneven. GPT never misses itself. Kimi
never finds itself. Observational bias exists, but it is
smaller than it looks. Most of the gap
is quality, not narcissism. Only Gemini shows a statistically
significant label effect — the name itself
moves the score. For Kimi, the self-penalty is actually
a quality signal. The model grades itself
harshly because its own responses genuinely scored
lower under blind review. The mirror test
doesn't measure vanity. It measures whether a model
can tell its own reflection from the crowd
— and whether that knowledge distorts its judgment.
If you are reading a benchmark, comparing
model outputs, or evaluating an AI's self-report, ask
yourself: does the score follow the name, or does
it follow the text? The answer matters
more than the number. Full replication data is available
on GitHub. - S01: ~25s (title /
hook) - S02: ~40s (experiment overview) -
S03: ~50s (recognition chart) - S04: ~60s
(observational bias chart) - S05: ~70s (causal
label swap chart) - S06: ~80s (quality-adjusted
residual chart) - S07: ~60s (conclusion /
takeaways) - Total target: ~385s (~6.4 min)